Finding aid for the Aldous and Laura Huxley papers, 1925-2007 LSC.2009
UCLA Library Special Collections
Aldous and Laura Huxley papers
1925-2007
UCLA Library Special Collections
Huxley, Aldous
Huxley, Laura Archera
LSC.2009
50.5 Linear Feet (110 boxes, 4 cartons, and 5 oversize boxes)
8 Audiovisual Carriers (7 records, 1 open reel audiotape)
10 Born-digital Carriers (9 optical discs, 1 floppy disk)
Aldous Leonard Huxley (1894-1963) was a prolific writer of novels, essays, poetry, criticism, and screenplays. The Aldous Huxley Papers portion of the collection consists correspondence between Aldous Huxley and publishers Harper & Row, personal correspondence, holographic notes, literary manuscripts and personal effects. Laura Archera Huxley (1911-2007) was a musician, author, psychological counselor and lecturer. The materials in the collection that comprise the personal papers of Laura Archer Huxley include personal correspondence, holographic and typewritten notes, manuscripts, collected articles and clippings and interviews. As well, there are photographs and audiovisual recordings of both Aldous Huxley and Laura Archera Huxley.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Collection partially assembled by the UCLA Library Special Collections staff by purchase and gift.
Gift of Harper & Row, 1972.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9917206393606533
Biography/History
Aldous Leonard Huxley was born on July 26, 1894 in Surrey, England; a disease of the eyes permanently weakened his vision at age 16, disrupting his plan to enter the medical profession; BA, Balliol College, Oxford, 1916; employed by the British government during World War I; schoolmaster at Eton College, 1917-19; staff member of Athenaeum and Westminster gazette, 1919-24; published his first novel, Chrome yellow, in 1921; went on to write Point counter point (1928), Brave new world (1932), Eyeless in Gaza (1936), and Island (1962), among others; was a prolific writer of essays, poetry, criticism, and screenplays; received D. Litt. from University of California in 1959; died on November 22, 1963 in California.
Laura Huxley was born on November 2, 1911 in Turin (Torino), Italy. Laura studied violin since the age of ten, and as a teenager, continued her studies of the instrument in Berlin, Paris, and Rome. She eventually toured Europe and the United States, performing at Carnegie Hall and further pursuing her music study at the Curtis Institute of Philadelphia.
During World War II, Laura decided to remain in the United States and live with her close friend --- sister to Ernest Hemingway's second wife, Pauline Pfeiffer Hemingway --- Virginia Pfeiffer. Laura Huxley's study in psychotherapy, health, and nutrition was prompted by Virginia Pfeiffer's diagnosis of cancer in 1949. Before her studies and career in well-being, psychology, and health, Laura Huxley worked in Hollywood. Aldous Huxley and his first wife, Maria, met Laura Archera in 1948 while living in Wrightwood, California. In 1955, Maria Huxley died of breast cancer. One year after Maria's death, Aldous and Laura were married in Yuma, California. Together, they moved into a home in Hollywood Hills on Deronda Drive. After their house and most of Aldous's personal manuscripts and library were burned in a fire on May 12, 1961, the couple moved in with Virginia Pfeiffer and her two adopted children.
In 1959, before the fire, Aldous Huxley presented a series of lectures at the University of California, Santa Barbara called "The Human Situation." In 1961, Huxley repeated a variation of "The Human Situation" in a lecture series he presented at M.I.T. when he was the Carnegie Visiting Professor in Humanities. Huxley also spoke on "Human Potentialities" at the Esalen Institute in Big Sur, California. In 1960, Aldous Huxley was diagnosed with laryngeal cancer. Aldous Huxley wrote and published his last novel, Island, in 1962. He died on November 22, 1963, the same day President John F. Kennedy was assassinated.
In 1963, Laura published her book, You Are Not the Target. She also offered psychological health and well-being guidance in the form of workshops and seminars to various groups and individuals in Southern California. Laura went on to publish a personal account of her life with Aldous in a book titled This Timeless Moment in 1969. Her later publications include Between Heaven and Earth: Recipes for Living and Loving (1974), Oneaday Reason to be Happy (1986) and The Child of Your Dreams (1987), co-authored with her nephew, Piero Ferrucci. In 1977, she founded a non-profit organization called, "Our Ultimate Investment" (OUI) which later became "Children: Our Ultimate Investment." The organization sponsored conferences on the topic of "the nurturing of the possible human" in 1978 and 1994. Among the awards and acknowledgments given to Laura Huxley in her life are an Honorary Doctorate in Human Services from La Sierra University and the Thomas R. Verny Award from the Association of Prenatal and Perinatal Psychology and Health in December of 2003. Laura Huxley died of cancer on December 13, 2007 in her Hollywood home.
Scope and Content
The first 10 boxes of this collection consist primarily of business correspondence between Aldous Huxley and publishers Harper & Row, personal correspondence, and literary manuscripts. Correspondents include Jacob Zeitlin, Lawrence Clark Powell, Gerald Heard, Lewis Mumford, Hugh Trevor-Roper, and Lionel Trilling. Literary manuscripts include The devils of Loudon and Time must have a stop.
Boxes 11-15 include the books from Aldous Huxley's personal library. These items are catalogued in the UCLA online library catalog.
Following the first 15 boxes, the additions to this original acquisition (added between 2009 to 2011) consist of personal papers, handwritten notes, typed drafts of articles, essays and novels, galleys, day calendars, sketchbooks, drafts of previously unpublished essays, collected clippings, journal articles, off-prints, magazines, personal effects such as pens, eyeglasses, eye patches, memberships cards and a passport.
The collection contains audio-visual materials such as sound recordings in reel and cassette tape formats as well as recorded film reels and VHS videos. The collection also contains photographs and assorted negatives.
The first level of organization of the additions has been arranged into two record groups according to their creator, either Aldous Huxley or Laura Huxley. The series under each record group reflect the materials and intellectual content of the material therein. The materials organized under the record group "Aldous Huxley Papers" are organized into series that are slightly different from the series organizing the "Laura Huxley Papers," reflecting the slightly different nature of the materials within the record group. The first 10 boxes of the collection were arranged and assigned series at an earlier time than the additions. For this reason the series organizing these first 15 boxes do not fall within the organizational schema applied to the additions to the collection. Therefore the correspondence in this record group "The Aldous Huxley Papers" can be found under a few different series: 'Correspondence' (Box 1) and 'Personal: Correspondence' (Boxes 48-49). Within a series there are often subseries categories that further organize the material. For example, under the 'Personal' series of "The Aldous Huxley Papers" are the subseries: Correspondence, [last writings on deathbed], Family Related, Personal Effects, Recordings, Research Related and Sketch. The subseries under the series 'Personal' in the Laura Huxley Papers section of the collection include: Collected by, Correspondence, Early Life, Film, Personal Effects, recordings, Video Recordings and Virginia Pfeiffer. The other series in the collection also have subseries categories, some of which are by media type such as 'Recordings,' while other subseries are the title of a work or lecture or the name of a correspondent.
Organization and Arrangement
The Aldous Huxley papers are arranged in the following series:
Correspondence (Box 1).
Literary manuscripts and interviews (Boxes 2-4,7-9)
Harper & Row correspondence (Boxes 5-6)
Correspondence and holograph of children's story (Box 10)
Novels, Essays and Articles (Boxes 16-21, 45-47, 50, 51, 56-59, 60-62, 64)
Lectures and Speeches (Boxes 22, 23, 46, 50, 56, 91-94, 97-99, 107, 114)
Writings About Aldous Huxley (Boxes 15, 41, 44, 46-47, 53, 64)
Retrospectives (Boxes 94-95, 98-100)
Writings Based on the Work of Aldous Huxley (Boxes 23-24, 47, 56)
Interviews (Boxes 4, 91-92, 94-95, 99, 101, 111, 112)
Personal (Boxes 41, 46, 48, 50, 55, 58, 63, 74-76, 82-86, 88-91, 97-101)
Psychedelics (Boxes 27, 85, 98, 100)
Contents of Grey Metal Box (Boxes 45, 80-81)
Photographs (Boxes 65-73, 77)
Safe Contents (Boxes 78-79)
Music (Boxes 85, 98, 99, 106)
The Laura Huxley papers are arranged in the following series:
Aldous Huxley Related Material (Boxes 42-44, 55-53)
Interviews (Boxes 85, 101-102, 106, 114)
Lectures and Speeches (Boxes 84, 99-100, 103-106, 113-115)
Music (Boxes 106, 114)
Novels, Essays and Other Written Works (Boxes 30, 33, 39, 51, 54, 107)
Research / Professional / Projects (Boxes 31-32, 37, 38, 40, 52-55)
Personal (Boxes 25-26, 34-36, 39, 55, 65, 69, 71, 75, 85-88, 111-112, 101-105, 108-110 )
Photographs (Boxes 65, 69-72, 77)
Psychedelics (Boxes 28-29, 52, 103, 105, 109, 115)
Manuscripts for publication; Authors, English -- 20th century -- Archives; Huxley, Laura Archera; Harper & Row, Publishers; Huxley, Aldous, 1894-1963--Archives.
- Letters
  - Fourteen Letters to Various Persons, 1928-1956
    - [], London. To Naomi Royde-Smith., 1928?; Holograph. (Box 1)
    - 4. iv. 28, London. To Arthur Wellings., Holograph. (Box 1)
    - [], London. To Harold John Massingham., May 1930; Holograph. (Box 1)
    - 8. v. 30, London. To Harold John Massingham., Holograph. (Box 1)
    - 28. xi. 30, Cap de la Gorguette, Sanary (Var) [France]. To Fenner Brockway., Holograph. (Box 1)
    - 7. i. 37, La Gorguette, Sanary (Var). To Mr. Duncan., Holograph. (Box 1)
    - [], La Gorguette, Sanary (Var). To C. Day Lewis., January 8, 1937; 2pp. Holograph. (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Answers Day Lewis's pamphlet attacking a pacifist pamphlet by Huxley published the previous year. Huxley argues that the military defence of democracy in contemporary circumstances entails the abolition of democracy even before war starts.
    - 13. viii. 40. Pacific Palisades. To Miss Elizabeth Bryan., Holograph. (Box 1)
    - 27. v. 41. Pacific Palisades. To Nathan Lippis., Holograph. (Box 1)
    - , Llano. To Edmund Sidney Pollock Haynes., March 25th, 1945; 3pp. Typescript. Printed on p.33 of this booklet. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Jake Zeitlin, 1937-1962
    The correspondence includes thirty-three items from Huxley, mostly holograph letters; a few holograph communications from Maria Huxley and one from Ellen Huxley, the author's wife and daughter-in-law respectively; carbon copies of twenty letters Jake Zeitlin wrote to Huxley; and a few letters to and from others, chiefly concerning business matters.
    - [], San Cristobal, New Mexico., June 1937; Holograph. (Box 1)
      Willing to let J.Z. handle film rights.
    - 12. vii. 37, San Cristobal, New Mexico., Typescript. (Box 1)
      Authorizes J.Z. to represent him, and comments on his works that he considers suitable for the films. Might be willing to work in Hollywood.
    - 10. xii. 37, Rhinebeck, New York., Holograph. (Box 1)
      Lecturing in the East, inquires about his scenario, will return to Europe if nothing doing in Hollywood.
    - 10. i. 38, Rhinebeck, New York., Typescript. (Box 1)
      About to return to California. "I am ruminating a novel, which threatens, if I am not careful, lo turn into the Comédie Humaine. Let's hope to God it can be restrained before it's too late!"
    - []., 1938; 2pp. Typescript. (Box 1)
      The untitled (original) typescript with a few holograph revisions of an essay written for J.Z. to celebrate the opening of his new bookshop: "The Most Agreeable Vice."
      Privately printed (500 copies) in Los Angeles, June 15, 1938.
    - 8. vi. 38, Los Angeles., Holograph. (Box 1)
    - 19. xi. 38, Los Angeles., Typescript. (Box 1)
      He thinks it futile for him to write a statement denouncing the Nazi persecution of the Jews.
    - 9. ix. 39, Pacific Palisades., Holograph. (Box 1)
      "I am at the studio all day and too much preoccupied with the War and its implications to want to do anything at night but meditate in solitude."
    - , Pacific Palisades., December 26, 1940; Typescript. (Box 1)
    - 5. v. 41, Pacific Palisades., Holograph. (Box 1)
      Sends foreword he has written for Ashley Montagu's book [Man's Most Dangerous Myth: The Fallacy of Race].
      Among the miscellaneous manuscripts in the Huxley-Zeitlin correspondence is the following jingle:
      "Whenever Aldous Huxley writes / A novel that delights / His followers / His brother Julian / At once indites / A learned work / On Coprolites / For scholars"
      by Ashley Montagu
    - , 20th Century-Fox Studios., July 24th, 1941; Typescript. (Box 1)
      Asks J.Z. to locate rare French books he needs to write about "the case of the diabolic possessions at Loudun, during the seventeenth century."
    - 7. VIII. 41, 20th Century-Fox Studios., Holograph. (Box 1)
      Encloses his check for $150 "as a loan for the publication of Dr. Montague's pamphlet."
    - [, Trabuco Canyon]., September 1942 (Box 1)
      A carbon copy of the prospectus of Trabuco College, founded during the war by Huxley, Gerald Heard, and others in the belief "that only through change of individual character can there be any real apprehension of God's nature and will, and a lasting change in civilisation or humanity."
      General note
      The prospectus was mimeographed for distribution in September 1942.
      Huxley's share cannot be determined, but he certainly had a hand in its composition.
    - , Llano., April 1, 1943; Holograph postcard. (Box 1)
    - , Llano., February 24, 1943; Typescript. (Box 1)
      "How nice of the Library people to make an exhibition of my books, and of you to take so much trouble with it!"
    - , Llano., April 25th, 1943; 2pp. Typescript. Printed on p.29. (Box 1)
    - , Llano., June 27, 1943; Typescript. (Box 1)
      "Demonology as such doesn't interest me—only the particular case of Loudun, because it happened to involve a very remarkable man, Father Surin. In itself, the subject is almost infinitely squalid—at once comical and loathsome, like all low-grade 'supernaturalism' that is preoccupied with evil."
    - [], Llano., November 28, 1944; Holograph postcard. (Box 1)
    - 29. III. 48, Wrightwood., Holograph. (Box 1)
    - [], "Leonardo, then and now.", 1952; Original typescript, two leaves, single-spaced, with a few holograph corrections. (Box 1)
      Published in an exhibit catalogue of the Municipal Art Commission of Los Angeles, Leonardo da Vinci, 500th Anniversary Exhibition, October 27th to November 16 (1952).
    - Huxley's "Doodles in the Dictionary," published in Esquire, September 1955., Carbon copy. (Box 1)
      The essay prompted by J.Z. when he showed Huxley the Latin-French dictionary owned and illuminated by Toulouse-Lautrec at 16.
    - 17. vi. 55, New York City., Holograph. (Box 1)
      Staying in George Kaufman's apartment, has finished his play [The Genius and the Goddess].
    - 27. vi. 55 [New York City]., Holograph. (Box 1)
    - , Guilford, Connecticut., August 18th, 1955 (Box 1)
      Thanks for finding a first edition of Congreve's Double Dealer, a present for George Kaufman.
    - , Los Angeles., June 4th, 1956; Holograph. (Box 1)
    - 27.x. 57, New York City. (Box 1)
      His play in rehearsal causes "many fatigues & frustrations."
    - [], Turin, Italy., October 31, 1958; Holograph note. (Box 1)
    - 4. XII. 60, Los Angeles., Holograph. (Box 1)
      Has been asked to sell manuscripts of St. Mawr, Point Counter Point, The Genius and the Goddess.
      "Am just back from 2 months as a Professor at MIT; & up to the eyes in work on a book which has kept me busy for the last 3 or 4 years."
    - 7. III. 61, Los Angeles., Holograph. (Box 1)
      "The DHL MS is still at the bottom of some trunk, & I have had no time to undertake a search for it. My own MSS are there too."
    - []., June 1961; Typescript. (Box 1)
      list of manuscripts, letters, and rare books destroyed by fire.
    - 2. III. 62, Berkeley., Holograph. (Box 1)
      Sends manuscripts of two recent essays, asking what price they might fetch. At Berkeley as "Visiting Professor of nothing in particular."
    - 28. III 62, Berkeley., Holograph. (Box 1)
      "Prefers not to sell the manuscript of Island at the moment."
    - 17. v. 62, Berkeley., Holograph. (Box 1)
      Thanks for selling a manuscript, but objects that J.Z. has taken no commission.
      "These transactions must be on a business basis, for I don't feel that old friendship gives me the right to exploit you."
  - Correspondence with Lawrence Clark Powell, 1940-1962
    In addition to sixteen Huxley items, the correspondence includes a half dozen carbon copies of Dr. Powell's letters to Huxley, and Dr. Powell's correspondence with an Illinois librarian, David K. Maxfield, about a translation of Lucian's The Mimes of the Courtesans signed "A.L.H." The University of Chicago Library catalogue identified the translator as Aldous Leonard Huxley, and Mr. Maxfield wrote to verify this attribution. When Dr. Powell forwarded the inquiry, Huxley replied that he was not the translator, although he later confessed, Dr. Powell reported, "to having forgotten some of his sins of authorship."
    - 27.iii.40, Pacific Palisades., Holograph. (Box 1)
      Declines invitation to give a talk.
    - [], Beverly Hills., May 15, 1942; Holograph postcard. (Box 1)
    - 12. vii. 43, Llano., Holograph. (Box 1)
      Thanks for the exhibition.
    - , Llano., September 18th, 1943; 2pp. Typescript. Printed on p.31 of this booklet. (Box 1)
    - 19. ix. 44, Llano., Holograph. (Box 1)
      "I was very glad to hear that you have succeeded to the librarianship at UCLA. I hope they give you enough money to buy the books you want."
    - , Llano., May 16th, 1945; Holograph. (Box 1)
      Letter of introduction to enable a young friend and assistant to use the Library.
    - [, Los Angeles]., November 3, 1949; Holograph postcard. (Box 1)
      "No, I never translated any Lucian & don't recall ever having written anything about the dialogues, tho' I greatly admire them."
    - January 7th, 1950., Holograph. (Box 1)
      "Unable to accept invitation to judge a student book-collecting contest."
    - , New York., May 1st, 1950; Holograph. (Box 1)
      "I have received a request from the Dutch Government to send a MS to the Cultural Exhibition at the Hague. I have nothing to hand & I wonder whether it would be a great trouble for you to send the one I gave you this spring." ["Variations on a Philosopher," which the Library in due course sent to The Hague].
    - 24. II. 52, Los Angeles., Holograph. (Box 1)
      Agrees to serve as judge in a book-collecting contest.
    - 17. ix. 52, Los Angeles., Holograph. (Box 1)
      Declines invitation to talk on Shaw, "whom I don't know at all well—perhaps because I have never found him very interesting. Did he, after all, ever know anything about human beings?"
    - [], Los Angeles., July 1956; Typescript. (Box 1)
      Requests interlibrary loan of two nineteenth-century books by the poet William Barnes illustrating his theory "that words of Latin or Greek origin were wicked and that everything in English could be expressed in words of Teutonic origin. (e.g. 'adjective' should be 'mark-word of suchness;' 'Omnibus' becomes 'folkwain.')."
      [An attached note from the Interlibrary Loan department reports that the books were borrowed from the Harvard Library for Mr. Huxley]
    - , Los Angeles., May 2nd, 1957; Holograph. (Box 1)
    - 27. xi. 60, Los Angeles., Holograph. (Box 1)
    - 27. III. 61, Los Angeles., Holograph. Reproduced on p.20. (Box 1)
    - []., Spring 1962; Typescript with holograph corrections and signature. (Box 1)
      Untitled statement on Tropic of Cancer written when Dr. Powell asked Huxley to appear as a defense witness at the Los Angeles court hearing. Published in Henry Miller and the Critics (Southern Illinois University Press, 1963).
    - Letters to Jake Zeitlin, 1943-1944, 1953 and 1963.; 6 items. Typescript. (Box 1)
      re Aldous Huxley.
    - Letter to Lawrence Clark Powell from Huntington Cairns. Washington, D.C., August 4, 1943.; Typescript, signed. (Box 1)
  - Aldous Huxley:
    - Letter to George Edward Howard. Lucca, Italy., 6 X 27. Holograph. (Box 1)
    - Letter to the editor of Ekstra Bladet. Los Angeles., 20 IX 37. Holograph. (Box 1)
    - Letter to William Davenport. Palm Desert, March 28th, 1949.; Typescript, signed. (Box 1)
    - Letters to Margaret Isherwood. Los Angeles., 20 III 55, 23 IX 56, 9 II 57. Holograph. 3 items. (Box 1)
    - Letter to Sam Eisenstein. Los Angeles., 31 XII 6 leaves. Photocopy of holograph letter. (Box 1)
    - Letters to Reid Gardner. Los Angeles., 25 VI 62. Holograph. Hampstead, England, 18 IX 62. Holograph. (Box 1)
    - Letter to Merle Armitage. Sanary, France, n.d.; Holograph. (Box 1)
    - Letters to Gerard Hopkins. London., 29 III 27, 26 iv 31. Holograph. 2 items. (Box 1)
    - Letters to Frances Petersen. v.p., v.d.; Holograph and typescript. 7 items (8 leaves). (Box 1)
- Literary Manuscripts
  - Along the Road. Notes and Essays of a Tourist. By Aldous Huxley., 96 leaves, typescript and holograph. (Box 2)
    Index page, 4 title pages, and 91 single-spaced, crowded pages of text.
    A carbon copy, evidently used by the published, for editor's notes are pencilled in. Numerous minor corrections and revision in Huxley's handon almost every page. Glued to the first page is a printed notice to publishers regarding copyright.
    Bibliography
    Published by Chatto & Windus, London, 1925; George H. Doran Company, New York, 1925.
  - Ape and Essence. A Play. By Aldous Huxley., 2 typescripts. (Box 2)
    2 different versions:
    Version I: 84 leaves with a few holograph revisions; slip inserted at p.63, with one typed speech.
    Version II: 87 leaves, paginated by acts.
    Both are carbon copies, both in binders of the William Morris Agency as submitted for motion picture consideration.
    Unpublished. The novel was published by Harper & Brothers, New York, 1948; Chatto & Windus, London, 1949.
  - Apocalypse. By Aldous Huxley., 2 folio leaves, holograph. (Box 2)
    Brief essay comparing modern utopian thinking with early Christian expectations of the Second Coming, and concluding "that the millenium, if ever it comes, will steal gradually upon the world."
    "Many professed atheists firmly believe that the Kingdom of God will be made manifest on earth, in their own life time. True, they do not call it the Kingdom of God; but in all essentials the Perfect State of their socialist or fascist imagination is indistinguishable from the transfigured earth of the Early Christian millenium. It is a world where truth, justice and mercy everywhere prevail; where reason dominates the passions; where men are exclusively their better selves. The Early Christians believed that this transformation would be accomplished by the direct intervention of a higher power. Their modern counterparts smile at this ingenuous faith; they believe in Organization. The world is out of joint; but Organization will set it right—at once, in our time."
    Published in the Chicago Herald and Examiner, August 19,1933.